<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Winston Kotzan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://winstonkotzan.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://winstonkotzan.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-27T23:26:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://winstonkotzan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Winston Kotzan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to debug anything in RubyMine]]></title>
    <link href="http://winstonkotzan.com/blog/2014/01/09/how-to-debug-anything-in-rubymine/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-09T14:19:59Z</updated>
    <id>http://winstonkotzan.com/blog/2014/01/09/how-to-debug-anything-in-rubymine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>RubyMine has an excellent step-through debugger which lets you set breakpoints in your code and trace through the
program. I use RubyMine’s debugger all the time and I find it to be an especially useful feature for exploring all of
the metaprogramming going on behind the scenes in Ruby on Rails. To run the debugger, simply set up a configuration
and hit the debug button on the toolbar. RubyMine will then launch the rails server in its own instance of the
command terminal, which you can view in the output window at the bottom of the screen.</p>

<p><img src="/resources/2014-01-09-how-to-debug-anything-in-rubymine/screen_layout.png" /></p>

<div class="caption">
Figure 1: RubyMine's trace debugger at work
</div>

<p>The debugger can only run by tying itself to a Ruby related command line program. In most cases this will be a call to
<code>Rails server</code>.  Using the “Edit Configurations” dialog box, you can use the debugger on other Ruby related
executables besides Rails such as Cucumber, RSpec, Rack, or IRB.</p>

<p><img src="/resources/2014-01-09-how-to-debug-anything-in-rubymine/edit_configurations_dialog.png" /></p>

<div class="caption">
Figure 2: The "Edit Configurations" dialog box. Notice how it does not provide an option for you
to run the debugger against an executable not on the list.
</div>

<p>But what if you want to use the debugger on a program not listed in the Edit Configurations box? For example, we might
be writing a plugin for the Jekyll blogging engine, or we might want to learn more about the metaprogramming behind
Nanoc. Alternative frameworks to Rails often have their own set of terminal commands for invoking the program. You might
have to run it by calling <code>jekyll build</code> or <code>nanoc compile</code>.</p>

<p>A simple hack for getting such programs to run in RubyMine’s debugger is to create a rake task which invokes the program
for you. In this example, I want to set a breakpoint in Nanoc’s Rules file. Since this isn’t a default in Rubymine’s
configuration, I can get around this limitation by calling Nanoc through a task in my Rakefile.</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption><span>Rakefile </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class="line-number">1</span>
<span class="line-number">2</span>
<span class="line-number">3</span>
<span class="line-number">4</span>
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="ruby"><span class="line"><span class="n">desc</span> <span class="s2">&quot;compile with nanoc&quot;</span>
</span><span class="line"><span class="n">task</span> <span class="ss">:compile</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class="line">  <span class="nb">system</span> <span class="s1">&#39;nanoc compile&#39;</span>
</span><span class="line"><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

<p>Now I can debug nanoc’s compiler by creating a debug configuration in RubyMine and setting it to call the rake
task I’ve created.</p>

<p><img src="/resources/2014-01-09-how-to-debug-anything-in-rubymine/rake_configuration.png" /></p>

<div class="caption">
Figure 3: The configuration in RubyMine to call my Rake task.
</div>

<p><img src="/resources/2014-01-09-how-to-debug-anything-in-rubymine/debugging_nanoc.png" /></p>

<div class="caption">
Figure 4: The debugger stoped at a breakpoint after calling the Nanoc compiler.
</div>

<p>Sometimes Ruby can be a confusing language because of all its metaprogramming. At times it is difficult to tell what
class an object might descend from, or which version of an overloaded method is getting called. RubyMine is an excellent
tool for helping you decipher the code behind Ruby gems and better understand how they are designed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disruptive Innovation Levels Information Asymmetry in Enterprise Software]]></title>
    <link href="http://winstonkotzan.com/blog/2014/01/04/disruptive-innovation-levels-information-asymemetry-in-enterprise-software/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-04T05:26:55Z</updated>
    <id>http://winstonkotzan.com/blog/2014/01/04/disruptive-innovation-levels-information-asymemetry-in-enterprise-software</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Selecting enterprise software is a daunting task that requires knowledge to make a good decision. A misguided outcome
could cost your organization a great deal in implementation expenses and lost productivity.  Unfortunately, the
information you may need to arrive at the right decision for your circumstance could be hard to find. Obscure product
websites, confusing suites of bundled features, and crafty sales people who are adept at upselling benefits all too
often obstruct the decision process. If only picking an enterprise software package were as simple as researching
reviews for a restaurant or comparing the latest iGadgets from Apple… but wait!</p>

<p>Now with <a href="http://www.g2crowd.com/" target="_blank">G2Crowd</a>, the wisdom of the cloud is here to help. Access thousands of reviews from users of all spectrums –
from managers to direct end users. G2 even has a useful Q&amp;A facility to prompt discussions by allowing you to ask other
users for their opinions on a given product.</p>

<p>G2Crowd is an incredible resource because no other place allows you to compare a wide variety of software packages side
by side. No longer will the marketing budgets of elephant-in-the-room vendors so easily drown out the smaller, more
nimble competition. For example, Salesforce.com is the go-to name in CRM but may not be the right solution for everyone.
Through product reviews and comparisons on G2Crowd you may find that a lesser known CRM alternative like Chicago’s own
Base CRM has a better set of features that’s right for you.</p>

<p>We’ve seen the Internet flatten information asymmetry in industries far and wide. Amazon.com is the comparison place
for goods of all sorts. Yelp will help you find the best place to dine in town. TripAdvisor will tell you where to
vacay. Now its time to level the playing field for the $180 billion global enterprise software market.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
